In 1956, a documentary by Jacques Cousteau won
في عام 1956، فاز فيلم وثائقي من إخراج جاك كوستو
both the Palme d'Or and an Oscar award.
بجائزة السعفة الذهبية وجائزة الأوسكار.
This film was called, "Le Monde Du Silence,"
كان عنوان هذا الفيلم "العالم الصامت".
The premise of the title was that the underwater world was a quiet world.
يستند العنوان على فرضية أن العالم تحت الماء كان عالمًا صامتًا.
We now know, 60 years later,
نحن نعلم الآن، بعد مرور 60 عامًا،
that the underwater world is anything but silent.
أن العالم تحت الماء هو كل شيء عدا كونه صامتًا.
Although the sounds are inaudible above water
على الرغم من أن الأصوات غير مسموعة على السطح،
depending on where you are and the time of year,
فإنه وحسب تموقعك والوقت من السنة،
the underwater soundscape can be as noisy as any jungle or rainforest.
يمكن للأصوات تحت الماء أن تكون صاخبة مثل أية أدغال أو غابة مطيرة.
Invertebrates like snapping shrimp, fish and marine mammals
إن اللافقاريات مثل الروبيان والأسماك وغيرها من الثدييات البحرية
all use sound.
كلها تستخدم الأصوات.
They use sound to study their habitat,
فهي تُصدر أصواتًا لتحليل مواطنها،
to keep in communication with each other,
والتواصل مع بعضها البعض،
to navigate,
والتنقل،
to detect predators and prey.
والكشف عن الحيوانات المفترسة والفريسة.
They also use sound by listening to know something about their environment.
وهي تستخدم الصوت أيضًا عبر الاستماع لدراسة بيئتها
Take, for an example, the Arctic.
فلنأخذ، على سبيل المثال، المنطقة القطبية الشمالية.
It's considered a vast, inhospitable place,
إذ تُعتبر منطقة شاسعة وغير مضيافة،
sometimes described as a desert,
وتوصف أحيانًا على أنها صحراء،
because it is so cold and so remote
لأنها شديدة البرودة ونائية
and ice-covered for much of the year.
ومغطاة بالجليد معظم أيام السنة.
And despite this,
ورغم ذلك،
there is no place on Earth that I would rather be than the Arctic,
لا يوجد أي مكان آخر على وجه الأرض يجذبني أكثر من المنطقة القطبية الشمالية،
especially as days lengthen and spring comes.
خاصة مع وصول الربيع حينما تصبح الأيام أطول.
To me, the Arctic really embodies this disconnect
بالنسبة لي، المنطقة القطبية الشمالية هي تجسيد مثالي لتلك الفجوة
between what we see on the surface and what's going on underwater.
بين ما نراه على السطح وما يحدث تحت الماء.
You can look out across the ice -- all white and blue and cold --
فإذا نظرت إلى الجليد، ستستشعر اللون الأبيض والأزرق والبرودة،
and see nothing.
لكنك لن تُبصر أي شيء.
But if you could hear underwater,
ولكن إذا استمعت إلى ما تحت الماء،
the sounds you would hear would at first amaze
فالأصوات التي ستسمعها ستدهشك في البداية
and then delight you.
ثم ستُمتعك للغاية.
And while your eyes are seeing nothing for kilometers but ice,
وحتى إن لم ترَ عيناك سوى كيلومترات من الجليد،
your ears are telling you that out there are bowhead and beluga whales,
فإن آذانك ستخبرك أن هناك حيتان مقوسة الرأس وأخرى بيضاء،
walrus and bearded seals.
وحيوان الفظ وعجل البحر الملتحي.
The ice, too, makes sounds.
والجليد، أيضًا، يُصدر أصواتًا.
It screeches and cracks and pops and groans,
فهو يُطلق صريرًا ويتصدَّع ويتشقق وينهار،
as it collides and rubs when temperature or currents or winds change.
حين يصطدم ويحتكُّ بسبب تغير درجة الحرارة أو التيارات أو الرياح.
And under 100 percent sea ice in the dead of winter,
وفي عمق 100 في المئة من الجليد البحري، في أوج الشتاء،
bowhead whales are singing.
تُغني الحيتان البيضاء.
And you would never expect that,
وهذا غير متوقع أبدًا،
because we humans,
لأننا نحن البشر،
we tend to be very visual animals.
نميل إلى كوننا حيوانات جد بصرية.
For most of us, but not all,
بالنسبة لمعظمنا، ولكن ليس كلنا،
our sense of sight is how we navigate our world.
فإن حسَّنا البصري هو طريقة تنقلنا في عالمنا.
For marine mammals that live underwater,
بالنسبة للثدييات البحرية التي تعيش تحت الماء،
where chemical cues and light transmit poorly,
حيث الإشارات الكيميائية والضوء المنخفض،
sound is the sense by which they see.
فالصوت هو الحاسة التي يرون بواسطتها.
And sound transmits very well underwater,
وينتقل الصوت بشكل جيد للغاية تحت الماء،
much better than it does in air,
أفضل بكثير مما يحدث في الهواء،
so signals can be heard over great distances.
لذا يمكن سماع الإشارات عبر مسافات بعيدة.
In the Arctic, this is especially important,
في المنطقة القطبية الشمالية، يُعَدُّ هذا أمرًا ضروريًا،
because not only do Arctic marine mammals have to hear each other,
لأنه لا يتوجب على هذه الثدييات البحرية الاستماع إلى بعضها البعض فقط،
but they also have to listen for cues in the environment
بل يتحتم عليها أيضًا الإصغاء إلى الإشارات في البيئة
that might indicate heavy ice ahead or open water.
والتي قد تُنذر بقرب نهر جليدي كبير أو مياه مفتوحة.
Remember, although they spend most of their lives underwater,
تذكَّروا أنه وعلى الرغم من كونها تقضي معظم حياتها تحت الماء،
they are mammals,
فهي تبقى ثدييات،
and so they have to surface to breathe.
ولذلك يجب عليها الصعود إلى السطح للتنفس.
So they might listen for thin ice or no ice,
إنها تُنصت، باحثة عن طبقات رقيقة من الجليد أو لا جليد،
or listen for echoes off nearby ice.
وقد تُنصت لأصداء منبعثة من جليد في مكان قريب.
Arctic marine mammals live in a rich and varied underwater soundscape.
تعيش الثدييات البحرية للقطب الشمالي، في عالم صوتي غني ومتنوع.
In the spring,
في الربيع،
it can be a cacophony of sound.
يمكن لهذا العالم أن يصبح مليئًا بالضوضاء.
(Marine mammal sounds)
(أصوات الثدييات البحرية)
But when the ice is frozen solid,
ولكن عندما يتجمد الجليد،
and there are no big temperature shifts or current changes,
ولا تكون هناك أية تغيرات كبيرة في درجة الحرارة أو التيارات،
the underwater Arctic has some of the lowest ambient noise levels
تتميز أعماق المنطقة القطبية الشمالية بضوضاء محيطية من بين أدنى المستويات
of the world's oceans.
في محيطات العالم.
But this is changing.
لكن هذا يتغير.
This is primarily due to a decrease in seasonal sea ice,
ويرجع ذلك أساسًا إلى انصهار الجليد البحري الموسمي،
which is a direct result of human greenhouse gas emissions.
وهذه نتيجة مباشرة للغازات الدفيئة البشرية.
We are, in effect, with climate change,
نحن في الواقع، ومع تغير المناخ،
conducting a completely uncontrolled experiment with our planet.
نقود تجربة على كوكبنا لا يمكن السيطرة عليها.
Over the past 30 years,
على مدى السنوات الثلاثين الماضية،
areas of the Arctic have seen decreases in seasonal sea ice
شهدت مواقع من المنطقة القطبية الشمالية انصهارًا للجليد البحري الموسمي
from anywhere from six weeks to four months.
خلال ما يتراوح بين ستة أسابيع إلى أربعة أشهر.
This decrease in sea ice is sometimes referred to as an increase
يُشار إلى هذا الانصهار في الجليد البحري أحيانًا على أنه تمديد
in the open water season.
لموسم المياه المفتوحة.
That is the time of year when the Arctic is navigable to vessels.
خلال هذا هو الوقت من السنة، يصبح بإمكان السفن التنقل في القطب الشمالي.
And not only is the extent of ice changing,
وليس سطح الجليد هو الوحيد الذي يتغير،
but the age and the width of ice is, too.
بل يتغير عمره وعرضه أيضًا.
Now, you may well have heard
ربما تكونون قد سمعتم
that a decrease in seasonal sea ice is causing a loss of habitat
أن انخفاضًا في الجليد البحري الموسمي يتسبب في فقدان المواطن
for animals that rely on sea ice,
للحيوانات التي تعتمد على جليد البحر،
such as ice seals, or walrus, or polar bears.
مثل أختام الجليد، أوالفظ أو الدببة القطبية.
Decreasing sea ice is also causing increased erosion along coastal villages,
كما أن انصهار الجليد يزيد من تآكل القرى الساحلية،
and changing prey availability for marine birds and mammals.
ويقلل من توفر الفرائس للطيور والثدييات البحرية.
Climate change and decreases in sea ice
إن الاحتباس الحراري وانصهار الجليد البحري
are also altering the underwater soundscape of the Arctic.
يعطلان بيئة الصوت في المنطقة القطبية الشمالية.
What do I mean by soundscape?
ما الذي أعنيه ببيئة الصوت؟
Those of us who eavesdrop on the oceans for a living
أولئك منا الذين ترتكز وظائفهم على الاستماع إلى المحيطات،
use instruments called hydrophones,
يستخدمون أداة تسمى الهيدروفون،
which are underwater microphones,
وهي ميكروفونات تحت الماء،
and we record ambient noise --
لتسجيل الأصوات المحيطة
the noise all around us.
والضوضاء التي تحيط بنا.
And the soundscape describes the different contributors
وتصف بيئة الصوت العوامل المختلفة
to this noise field.
لهذا المجال الصوتي.
What we are hearing on our hydrophones
ما نسمعه بالهيدروفون
are the very real sounds of climate change.
هي الأصوات الحقيقية للاحتباس الحراري.
We are hearing these changes from three fronts:
نحن نسمع هذه التغييرات من ثلاث جبهات:
from the air,
من الهواء،
from the water
ومن الماء،
and from land.
ومن الأرض.
First: air.
أولاً: الهواء.
Wind on water creates waves.
تُحدث الرياح أمواجًا على الماء.
These waves make bubbles;
هذه الأمواج تصنع فقاعات؛
the bubbles break,
تنفجر الفقاعات،
and when they do,
وعندما يحدث ذلك،
they make noise.
فإنها تُحدث ضوضاء.
And this noise is like a hiss or a static in the background.
وهذه الضوضاء تشبه الصفير أو التداخل الكهرومغناطيسي.
In the Arctic, when it's ice-covered,
في المنطقة القطبية الشمالية، عندما تكون مغطاة بالجليد،
most of the noise from wind doesn't make it into the water column,
فإن معظم الضوضاء الناتجة عن الرياح لا تصل إلى عمود الماء،
because the ice acts as a buffer between the atmosphere and the water.
لأن الثلج يعمل كحاجز بين الغلاف الجوي والماء.
This is one of the reasons
هذه هي أحد الأسباب
that the Arctic can have very low ambient noise levels.
التي تجعل مستويات الضوضاء المحيطة بالمنطقة القطبية الشمالية منخفضة للغاية.
But with decreases in seasonal sea ice,
لكن ومع انصهار الجليد البحري الموسمي،
not only is the Arctic now open to this wave noise,
لم تعد المنطقة القطبية الشمالية معرضة لهذه الضوضاء الموجية فقط،
but the number of storms and the intensity of storms in the Arctic
بل إن عدد العواصف وشدتها في المنطقة
has been increasing.
آخذة في الازدياد.
All of this is raising noise levels in a previously quiet ocean.
كل هذا يرفع مستويات الضوضاء في محيط هادئ سابقًا.
Second: water.
ثانيًا: الماء.
With less seasonal sea ice,
يؤدي انصهار الجليد الموسمي،
subarctic species are moving north,
إلى هجرة الأنواع شبه القطبية إلى الشمال،
and taking advantage of the new habitat that is created by more open water.
واستفادتها من الموطن الجديد الناتج عن ارتفاع المياه المفتوحة.
Now, Arctic whales, like this bowhead,
إن حيتان المنطقة القطبية الشمالية، كهذا الحوت مقوس الرأس،
they have no dorsal fin,
لا تملك أية زعنفة ظهرية،
because they have evolved to live and swim in ice-covered waters,
لأنها تطورت للعيش والسباحة في مياه مغطاة بالجليد،
and having something sticking off of your back is not very conducive
ووجود زعنفة بارزة من الظهر
and may, in fact, be excluding animals from the ice.
وقد يكون في الحقيقة سببًا في استبعاد الحيوانات عن الجليد.
But now, everywhere we've listened,
لكننا الآن، وحيثما أنصتنا،
we're hearing the sounds of fin whales and humpback whales
فإننا نسمع أصوات حيتان الزعانف والحيتان الحدباء
and killer whales,
والحيتان القاتلة،
further and further north,
في أقاصي الشمال،
and later and later in the season.
وفي وقت جد متأخر من الموسم.
We are hearing, in essence,
نحن نستمع، في الواقع،
an invasion of the Arctic by subarctic species.
لغزو للمنطقة القطبية الشمالية من طرف الأنواع شبه القطبية.
And we don't know what this means.
ونحن لا نعرف ما يعنيه هذا.
Will there be competition for food between Arctic and subarctic animals?
هل ستكون هناك منافسة من أجل الغذاء بين الحيوانات القطبية وشبه القطبية؟
Might these subarctic species introduce diseases or parasites into the Arctic?
هل ستجلب الأنواع شبه القطبية الأمراض أو الطفيليات إلى المنطقة القطبية الشمالية؟
And what are the new sounds that they are producing
وكيف تؤثر الأصوات التي تصدرها
doing to the soundscape underwater?
على بيئة الصوت تحت الماء؟
And third: land.
ثالثًا: الأرض.
And by land ...
وأقصد بالأرض ...
I mean people.
البشر.
More open water means increased human use of the Arctic.
فازدياد المياه المفتوحة يعني زيادة استغلال البشر للمنطقة القطبية الشمالية.
Just this past summer,
خلال هذا الصيف الماضي فقط،
a massive cruise ship made its way through the Northwest Passage --
عبرت سفينة سياحية ضخمة الممر الشمالي الغربي،
the once-mythical route between Europe and the Pacific.
الذي كان في يوم من الأيام الطريق الأسطوري بين أوروبا والمحيط الهادئ.
Decreases in sea ice have allowed humans to occupy the Arctic more often.
سمح انصهار الجليد للبشر باحتلال المنطقة القطبية الشمالية مرارًا.
It has allowed increases in oil and gas exploration and extraction,
مما أدى إلى زيادة في استخراج واستخدام النفط والغاز،
the potential for commercial shipping,
وزيادة الشحنات التجارية المحتملة
as well as increased tourism.
فضلاً عن زيادة السياحة.
And we now know that ship noise increases levels of stress hormones in whales
ونحن نعلم الآن أن ضجيج السفن يرفع من مستويات هرمونات التوتر لدى الحيتان
and can disrupt feeding behavior.
ويمكن أن يعطل سلوك التغذية.
Air guns, which produce loud, low-frequency "whoomps"
إن مسدسات الهواء الساخن، التي تنتج أصواتًا منخفضة التردد
every 10 to 20 seconds,
كل 10 إلى 20 ثانية،
changed the swimming and vocal behavior of whales.
قد غيرت من سلوكيات السباحة والصوت عند الحيتان.
And all of these sound sources are decreasing the acoustic space
وكل هذه المصادر الصوتية تقلل المساحة الصوتية
over which Arctic marine mammals can communicate.
التي يمكن للثدييات البحرية في المنطقة أن تتواصل عبرها.
Now, Arctic marine mammals are used to very high levels of noise
اعتادت هذه الثدييات البحرية على مستويات عالية جدًّا من الأصوات
at certain times of the year.
في أوقات معينة من السنة.
But this is primarily from other animals or from sea ice,
ولكن هذه الأصوات تنبعث أساسًا من الحيوانات الأخرى أو من الجليد البحري،
and these are the sounds with which they've evolved,
وهذه هي الأصوات التي عاشت معها،
and these are sounds that are vital to their very survival.
وهذه هي الأصوات الضرورية لبقائها.
These new sounds are loud and they're alien.
هذه الأصوات الجديدة صخبة وغريبة.
They might impact the environment in ways that we think we understand,
وقد تؤثر على البيئة بطرق نعتقد أننا نستوعبها،
but also in ways that we don't.
ولكنها تؤثر عليها أيضًا بطرق نجهلها.
Remember, sound is the most important sense for these animals.
لا تنسوا أن السمع هو أهم حاسة بالنسبة لهذه الحيوانات.
And not only is the physical habitat of the Arctic changing rapidly,
ليست المواطن الطبيعية لهذه المنطقة هي التي تتغير بسرعة فحسب،
but the acoustic habitat is, too.
بل إن المواطن الصوتية بدورها تتغير.
It's as if we've plucked these animals up from the quiet countryside
يبدو الأمر كما لو أننا قد أخذنا هذه الحيوانات من الريف الهادئ
and dropped them into a big city in the middle of rush hour.
وذهبنا بها إلى مدينة كبيرة ثم أطلقنا سراحها خلال ساعة الذروة.
And they can't escape it.
ولا تملك سبيلا للفرار.
So what can we do now?
إذن ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل الآن؟
We can't decrease wind speeds
لا يمكننا تقليل سرعة الرياح
or keep subarctic animals from migrating north,
أو منع الحيوانات شبه القطبية من الهجرة إلى الشمال،
but we can work on local solutions
ولكن يمكننا العمل على حلول محلية
to reducing human-caused underwater noise.
للحد من الأصوات المنبعثة من الأنشطة البشرية تحت الماء.
One of these solutions is to slow down ships
أحد هذه الحلول هو إبطاء السفن
that traverse the Arctic,
العابرة للمنطقة القطبية الشمالية،
because a slower ship is a quieter ship.
لأن إبطاءها سيجعلها أكثر هدوءً.
We can restrict access in seasons and regions
يمكننا تقييد الوصول خلال المواسم وإلى المناطق
that are important for mating or feeding or migrating.
التي تعتبر مهمة للتزاوج أو التغذية أو الهجرة.
We can get smarter about quieting ships
فلنكن أكثر حكمة بشأن السفن،
and find better ways to explore the ocean bottom.
ونبحث عن طرق أفضل لاستكشاف قاع المحيط.
And the good news is,
الخبر السار
there are people working on this right now.
هو أن هناك أشخاصًا يعملون لهذا الغرض حاليًا.
But ultimately,
ولكن في نهاية المطاف،
we humans have to do the hard work
يتعين علينا نحن البشر القيام بالجزء الصعب
of reversing or at the very least decelerating
وعكس أو على الأقل إبطاء
human-caused atmospheric changes.
تغيرات الغلاف الجوي التي يسببها الإنسان.
So, let's return to this idea of a silent world underwater.
فلنعد إلى فكرة العالم الصامت تحت الماء.
It's entirely possible
من المرجح جدًا
that many of the whales swimming in the Arctic today,
أن العديد من الحيتان الموجودة في مياه المنطقة القطبية الشمالية اليوم،
especially long-lived species like the bowhead whale
خاصة الأنواع طويلة العمر مثل الحوت مقوس الرأس،
that the Inuits say can live two human lives --
والتي يمكن أن تعيش لما يعادل حياة اثنين من البشر، وفقًا للإنويت،
it's possible that these whales were alive in 1956,
من الممكن أن هذه الحيتان كانت حية في عام 1956،
when Jacques Cousteau made his film.
عندما قام جاك كوستو بتصوير فيلمه.
And in retrospect,
إذا أعدنا النظر،
considering all the noise we are creating in the oceans today,
وباعتبار كل الضجيج الذي نُحدثه في المحيطات اليوم،
perhaps it really was "The Silent World."
ربما كان فعلًا "العالم الصامت".
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)